computer had Tony really not see you
again and we've been having these
wonderful conversations with Bill Reid
and Ben Haggard and Bill sharp yeah it's
been really stimulating and interesting
so the alchemy of ideas coming together
for me it's been it been greatest the h3
uni tribe in the IFF tribe join with
with the Regenesis tribe because I've
always felt that and they've been
somewhat drinking from similar fountains
and there's a lot of overlap as we're
discovering in the conversations but the
focus of this call and and also this
this recording is that I would love to
learn more and also share with people
listening the structure and the content
of the course on facilitating
transformational journeys that you've
been putting together within h3 Union
and it just looks wonderful and it
starts on May 20th and could you just
tell me talk me through that the seven
sessions of this course a little bit yes
I'm very happy to but before I do that
I'd just like to set the scene a little
bit um as you know and hopefully at
least some of your readers will know
that h3 uni is set up an online resource
library in which a number of methods of
facilitation and co-creative cooperation
are codified so that they become tools
that people can use for new kinds of
meeting that are acknowledging it at the
very start that this is a voyage into
the unknown and we have to create our
future as much as monitor what's going
on and respond to it so the difficulty
with such a resource library is of
course it's uni-dimensional
and particularly with the legacy of
analytical thinking that's throughout
society there's always a danger of there
being a tool trap that we think if we've
got the tool we've got the skill to use
it so what I'm setting out to do in this
course is to share some of them all
subtle unless easy aspects of getting
the best out of the methods and to to
keep that simple if you can think of it
as excuse me three overlapping circles
one circle is the existential by which I
mean the challenges that we have the
goggle problem Artie whether we're
focused on climate change or bio
recovery or urban development whatever
it is it's all part of the big system of
planet Earth
and so even very local initiatives have
to take account of the whole and we
certainly had that robbed in more than
our faces through the kovat 19 of
pandemic the second circle is the
methodology itself and here the
important thing is that the methods that
have got us to here through in a sense
non-systemic conceptual and practical
tools are unsuitable for getting us into
this new world of synergy and
interconnectedness so the toolkit we've
assembled and it's going to be growing
over the years as well is it all
directed towards connected patterns and
REE patterning things to just excuse me
a moment the the third circle is the
personal which is basically the idea
that if we're going to help transform
the world we have
to also and immediately transform
ourselves and that gets us into the
interesting area of spiritual
development whichever form we're taken
up within I think that if we ourselves
can't observe ourselves change our way
of even belief systems then we're going
to kid ourselves about the
transformation effect so the
transformation effect in our view comes
together when these three circles
coincide and then an interesting kind of
chemistry or alchemy takes place so I
hope to give a flavor of that in the
course so the next step in into the into
the course itself is just simply looking
at this way that on the one hand we live
on planet earth with a biosphere and all
the other living and material
complications and on the other hand we
live in a human world and historically
these two are separate disjunct and
particularly the one exploiting the
other the humans as parasites rather
than as members of the living system and
to bring these together we need some
kind of a bridge so the idea of the of
the course is that it's built around
five arches or steps in this bridge the
first one is understanding the world the
planet
where we are and this is based on a tool
that I now call the world mandala it
used to be called the world system model
and it still is in a sense but I want to
bring out with the word mandala that
it's much more about directing our inner
attention to things rather than doing
systems thinking in the more linear
deterministic way it's looking for
patterns of connection that are
important and we've seen a lot of these
come out inadvertently for us in the
pandemic so if you've got a project you
need to look at it in the context of the
world this helps you to do that
having done that you're then faced with
a considerable complexity more than we
used to normally handling so you need a
tool for that and this is where the idea
of what we call hexagon clustering comes
in the idea of the hexagon is it's a
six-sided object and normally when we
work with ideas we list them and they
have no connections or we draw a few
balloons in a few lines and call it a
system the beauty of the hexagon is it's
multivalent you can have up to six
connections of any idea or piece of
information with any other of course
some people will say well why only six
and the answer is if somebody can show
me a a tile that will tessellate with
more than six connections I'd be very
interested but that's the geometry of
the universe that we have also since we
normally work in checklists which have
no valency at all and this is a huge
step forward now when we've got
clustered information it's qualitative
it's not arrived at by big data type
methodology it's arrived up by conscious
perception we can then say okay how do
we want to get through to a decent
future through this complexity and that
leads us into the next tool which is the
three horizons and that's probably the
one that's most familiar to people
who've been into h3 Union in fact it's
where we derive our name the University
the third horizon and in the three
horizons of course we look at the
degrading world as horizon one the one
that we're so that we sort of run away
with us
we develop a vision of the future that
we we aspire to or desire which is
horizon 3 but these are in two different
paradigms two different patterns and you
can't flow from one into the other this
is where it differs from for example in
McKinsey 3 horizon model because horizon
2 is the difficult transition of
turbulence deconstruction reconstruction
innovation and is basically riddled with
dilemmas
so we first of all just sorry should be
a chipping one you can army and flow
here I just wanted to share with you
something that happened to me personally
with regard to to three horizons lately
is that I've certainly seen that the the
framing of the first and the third
horizon is very similar to Janna Macy's
wonderful framing of having to hospice
the old system out of existence and
Midwife the new system into existing and
that's the great transition in
in-between which is there that the
second horizon and for me it was just
powerful to put those like the D
hydrology work that reconnects lens
because what you were just starting with
is to say those two systems the human
system and the buyers system have never
been separate but the big journey is to
heal the unbroken whole and and I and
and that's how it actually Maps
perfectly on the work that reconnects
and even if if most people look at the
three horizon model as something may be
much more mental and less emotional but
it is actually no it's it's hugely
emotional in practice if applied you
know it really challenges our belief
systems how we feel about things what
we're willing to let go of what we
willing to take up the only qualifier
I'd put on your observation is that I
think it's it's it's as well as the
hospice bit
for horizon-1 there is the evolutionary
component of what is it about the last I
don't know whether you call it 300 or
even 2000 years that we developed as
humanity on the planet that is necessary
worth keeping but it needs refurbishing
repositioning and playing a different
role I find that that that is actually
very often when I work with the three
horizon with people when you point
particularly if it's it's a kind of
biased echo chamber group that is all
about the third horizon and to kind of
look at the red line at the bottom right
corner of the graph and say look at the
line is still here the old system
completely disappeared what is it that
we value and we want to keep it keep
having people people really kind of go
oh wow okay that's a question of them
ask myself and it's a vital question
because otherwise we throw out the baby
with the bath which we always do in in
the paradigm shift type framing I
personally have a preference for
holistic health and medical approaches
but another tool or sure I just want to
get rid of vaccination with it's very
sophisticated molecular bioscience
you know their desert there's a place
for for everything which is sort of
helpful and nonviolent I think that the
main contamination of horizon one is the
negative emotions I think I've just been
recently reading the sermons of
bodhidharma the fifth patriarch of Zen
and he says that that the problem with
becoming inlined is the three poisons I
think they're fear greed and delusion so
so transiting across from the first of
the third horizon has some
challenging factors which is why I call
this course facilitating transformative
journeys so I'll say a little bit more
about that now to wrap up but having got
that polarity between H 1 and H 3 we
have to live in the real world with real
people and real interests and how do we
bring people along we can't have an
idealistic future you know that only
three people espouse when they're
approaching 10 billion on the planet so
there has to be an inclusive ot and that
gets us into the world of dilemmas and
how to move from an either/or conflict
into a both/and but with both
transforming so you know to put it very
crudely in dilemma navigation the good
guys have to give up something as well
as the bad guys to arrive at the
generative third factor and I think
that's what your regenerative cultures
is about that that the the key of the
dilemma resolution journey is following
the trail of questions yes there are
answers along the way but there are only
way stations and the situation would
change again and again and we have to
learn a whole new level of flexible
intelligence and what what that does
also is that when you try to share
questions with somebody it's it's less
polarizing then if you try to hum out
what the right solution or answer is and
like I I constantly feel that
particularly now where so many people
are online and there's there's so many
ideas of what's going on and throwing
around and and some of it is conspiracy
theory and and quite a bit of mind
pollution and they're like bits of truth
mixed up with lots of fluff
and that ends up driving a sort of
polarization where people just other
other people based on our you mentioned
the word whatever just recently I had
somebody go off on me because I was
talking about circular economy and
giving me all the right critiques of a
sort of over sold Ellen MacArthur type
circular economy argument but not
wanting to listen to me anymore because
they'd already put me into a box of
saying oh that's one of those people who
sell snake oil instead of saying no
there's a nuanced dilemma to navigate
that we need an industrial system at an
industrial scale for some things that we
would like to have in society and and
yes we don't need it at these massive
circular European circular economy scale
we needed more more more regionalized
more localized but we have to have that
conversation around these questions in
order to move forward together rather
than standstill and and just argue so
sorry yeah well know that that's a very
good point because that experience is
why what I call the third circle of
personal development is so critical that
if you know our education is very much
based on I'm right you're wrong or if
there's a question there's a right
answer and there's an expert who knows
it and so kind of what our educational
mission is is to open up that as you are
the the whole world that it's
intelligent questioning that we need and
to play down the right answer I think
one of my teachers put it as a journey
of progressive approximation using a
kind of mathematical metaphor
anyhow having perhaps found some
guidelines of a pathway out of that
stage the fifth stage is convening wise
action and here we group of people
together in some way I have to bring
about it
transformational change and that
required wisdom and balance and so the
the use of some form of indigenous
wisdom circle is very helpful here that
one of my colleagues has translated into
a form that will sit more comfortably in
our culture but the essence of it is if
we're not a as a group to share a
consciousness of looking from multiple
perspectives simultaneously and then
meditating on that and arriving at the
decision the decision is four then you
have to do something because doing
nothing is a decision as well
probably ill-informed but on the other
hand it's got a half life it's only you
know until you situations evolve the
next cycle of learning and decision
making now having said those five things
of course is seven because the first one
is about taking the necessary synergy so
it brings in the idea of synergy which i
think is a bigger idea than systems
thinking but includes it and and the
final session is more only so will be
about facilitating how do we how do we
particularly link these three circles
together now all that's online in each
session is two hours so the thing that's
been exercising is how do we create a
kind of to use a metaphor a homeopathy
of our methods now we're a diluted very
small dose of something will actually
have the requisite effect it's a much
more potent level than the usual webinar
ish talking you know like this on on a
web
and so we have so evidence that we can
get a little bit better than that so
we're gonna carry on that route and I
hope that that's great I never I've
never described it that briefly before I
hope it's not too unintelligible no I
thought it was really useful and I mean
I'll share the link to the course
description along with this so people
can kind of listen to you while they
look at the the website the the the one
question - both seven two hour sessions
what kind of format did do you envision
for them roughly well I'm trying to mix
a number of ingredients because I've all
learned that we go nuts after even an
hour of zooming unless it's a very
intense reason being together and so two
hours is actually quite a long attention
stretch but if this was a face-to-face
workshop we clearly have as well as some
talking we'd have some discussion we'd
have some exercises we'd have some
reflective feedback and so on so the the
format will be flexible but basically
there'll be an introduction of the key
notion of the method and since this is a
visual facilitation approach there's a
big emphasis on diagrams but how to use
diagrams facilitative ly rather than
analytically and conceptually they'll be
everyone has to bring a project or more
than one project to the course that they
are us to work on as their laboratory
for applying the methods to to see what
they get hmm and they'll be feedback on
that and I'll be more in a coaching role
to say well stuck on that Brian little
interesting your observation of them
of getting this book here is just what
you know Charlie and Mary need in the
group who said they got stuck you know
you can so that there's a kind of begin
to be immutable and then there'll be a
little bit about you know where is this
being used use cases to give people
confidence that it can be done there may
be people in the group of tried some of
this and can also share their experience
and then there'll be some quick guidance
into the resource library so the people
for any approach realized they've got a
toolkit and her tool bag on the on the
web and um and hopefully even enough
time for some open Q&A and reflection
just to share you know being together as
a learning circle I'm really excited
that finally I mean this has been
cooking for a long time in the
conversations when was the meeting that
we had where Robert Fripp was then
Alfonso month we read IFF meeting where
we know it's about right twenty Twenty
twenty sixteen nothing yeah and that was
really early trying to state so it's a
exactly what four years ago yeah and and
I I thought well this is something we're
going to do in the next six months
what I find really exciting is they did
the synergy of an earlier version of the
five five core components conversation
we had sometime last September and this
reason element of somebody from a UK
Council saying I would like to go on
this this journey with my consulate and
explore it is just a wonderful example
of how this transformational journey
could also be offered more enhanced this
vision of h3 uni inside where
a group of people in a in a public
authority or an organization come
together and say we could learn all
these methodologies as we go on the
journey with this course together and
then rather than each one bringing their
own projects the the whole cohort can
actually between the session and then
get the feedback I think it's it's a
powerful format not just as an
educational program but actually as a
capacity building program within
organizations well as you know in a
previous stage in my life I worked a lot
on the idea of learning organizations
and worked with people I carried a
hearse and you know the work Peter sang
he was doing and it was very difficult
to get a learning organization and just
listening to you now it struck me oh
hang on maybe we can make a fresh go at
this which would be marked contrast as I
mean one University in the Middle East
has breath taking this Oh
asking me to do a short version as if it
wasn't short enough for a sort of a ph.d
program is more at the research academic
end but the real meat and potatoes as it
worries is some if I'm allowed to use
the word meat these days is that the you
know get getting on with real
transformation I've just read through a
paper on the contingency resilience
planning for a whole area in northern
England and I'm very impressed with the
range in complexity that these almost ad
hoc groups of people have to put
together and I think that with these
kinds of tools and the kind of
confidence of making the journey
hopefully it would be a great books for
that kind of
situation well who knows we're gonna be
I might be working on an opportunity to
run this course together with them with
some people in Portugal as well well I
think that's really great
no I hope I hope that I hope that we may
have reached a point with this work that
is it's got sufficient sort of self
generating integrity that we can truly
share it and share it in a way where
whoever sort of partners into it is also
bringing their own learning their own
contribution and the whole thing sort of
begins to spread let's call it the
regenerative effect shall we Daniel
yogurt culture exactly just supposing it
takes exactly wonderful and I think we
should keep this recording relatively
short the Suites of Europe but yet
there's a I'll stop now but thanks so
much for taking the time to introduce
the course and I'm looking forward to
you know landing page reference where
they can see the seven steps and tap
into some more you know the kind of
background that I'm being laying out
there anyhow thank you Dan Li I feel
much clearer about my own course now
it's very good exercise to also it on
the spot one thing that that should be
highlighted is that because it actually
is of course as you started off with
that is taking you through a set of
tools that is that are already freely
shared on the h3 on the resource library
it actually is a blended learning course
in the sense it's you you don't only get
the seven sessions you also get a huge
amount of rich material that will make a
lot more sense to you with the seven
sessions so um yeah I'm looking forward
to it so I'm just going to stop there